Guide to the Elmer Ellsworth Brown Papers MC.16
New York University Archives
- Series VI: Personal and professional correspondence, 1869-1911
  - Michigan, University of (student), 1887-1889 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Halle-Wittenberg, University of (graduate student), 1889-1890 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Jackson, Michigan (high school principal), 1890-1891 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Michigan, University of (acting Assistant Professor of Science and Art of Teaching), 1891-1892 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1892 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1893 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1894 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1895 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1896 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1897 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1898 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1899 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1900 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1901 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1902 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1903 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1904 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1905 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1906 January-June (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Department of Pedagogy: Student Enrollment, Class Reports, Miscellaneous Reports, 1892-1897, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Notebook for Courses, "Theory of Education" and "School Systems", 1897, 1899 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Oakland Public School Reports; Alameda County Teachers' Institute, 1892-1896 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Department of Pedagogy: Printed Material, 1892-1903, undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - California, University of: General University Printed Material, 1889-1901, undated (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1906 July-1906 Dec. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Letter Book (outgoing), 1906 July- 1907 May (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1907 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Letter Book (outgoing), 1907-1908 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1908 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Letter Book (outgoing), 1908 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1909 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1910 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Commissioner of Education (Department of the Interior): Correspondence, 1911 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - New York University (Chancellor): Correspondence, 1911 (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Series VII: Pre-retirement awards and tributes, 1905-1933
  The bulk of this material relates to various awards and tributes bestowed upon Brown for his service as educator and particularly, for his leadership of New York University. Included are congratulatory letters for twenty years of service in 1931, and his receipt of the Commendatore of the Order of the Crown of Italy in 1932, and the Order of the Crown of Belgium in 1933.
  - Louisiana Purchase Exposition Company: International Exposition of Industry and Labor, 1905-1906, 1913 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - New York University Law School Alumni Association: Annual Banquet, 1912 March (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Testimonial Dinner Honoring EEB on Fifteen Years of Service at N.Y.U. November 8, 1926 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - LL.D. Degree Conferred by the University of the State of New York, October 16, 1930 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Letters of Congratulations on Twenty Years of Service at N.Y.U., 1931 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Letters of Congratulations on Twenty Years of Service at N.Y.U., 1931 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Commendatore of the Order of the Crown of Italy, March 24, 1932 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Order of the Crown of Belgium, April 11, 1933, 1933 April-May (Box 24, Folder 8)
- Series VIII: Retirement, 1932-1935
  These files include announcements of Brown's retirement from the chancellorship of New York University, reactions and responses from friends and colleagues, material relating to a retirement dinner held in his honor on May 3, 1933, correspondence concerning his illness, the establishment of the Brown House for English studies on the University Heights campus of NYU, and papers relating to his European trip taken shortly before his death in 1934.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1932 April-October (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Response from Friends, Colleagues, and Organizations includes reaction to selection of Harry W. Chase as EEB's successor), 1932-1933 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - NYU Council-Minute of Appreciation, 1933 May 22 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Retirement Dinner, May 3, 1933: Programs, Speeches, Clippings, 1933 January-July (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Retirement Dinner, May 3, 1933: Testimonial Book with Signatures (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Retirement Dinner, May 3, 1933: Correspondence, 1933 April-May (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Retirement Dinner, May 3, 1933: Correspondence, 1933 May (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, including references to final illness, 1933 May-December (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, including references to final illness, 1934-1935 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Award of the Legion d'honneur, August 12, 1933, 1933-1935 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Brown House for English Studies: Letter to Finley J. Shephard and Newspaper Clipping, 1933-1934 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - European Trip, January 21 to April 3, 1934, 1933-1934 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Browning, Edward W.: Will re: Browning Prize, 1934 October (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Series IX: Obituaries, funeral arrangements, and memorial service, 1932-1935
  These files include announcements of Elmer E. Brown's death, funeral arrangements, a memorial service held on January 17, 1935, and Brown's personal effects, which include insurance policies, calling cards, passport, and various clippings.
  - Announcements, Obituaries, Funeral Arrangements, Acknowledgments, 1932, 1934 November (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Memorial Service, January 17, 1935 and Post-Death Tributes, 1934-1935 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Memorial Book and Letters of Acknowledgment, 1935 March-December (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Personal Effects: check stubs, Corn Exchange Bank Trust Co.; abridgment of Murray's English Grammar... (1823); wallet containing calling cards, clippings, and hotel credit cards; miscellaneous quotations; passport; fire insurance policy; photograph of Fanny Brown; typescript of prayer; Bible alphabet., undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
- Series X. Estate papers, 1932-1936
  The Brown estate papers include a copy of his will, an insurance policy, legal correspondence regarding stock holdings, income tax papers, miscellaneous vouchers, canceled checks and bank statements, distribution of bequests, and other miscellaneous papers.
  - Will, Life Insurance Policy, circa 1930s (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Legal Correspondence re: Stock, 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Income Tax Papers, 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Ralph Folks and David Samuels, Attorneys, 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Vouchers (miscellaneous), 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Rent Vouchers, 1934 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Cancelled Checks and Bank Statements, 1934-1936 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Receipts and Checks (miscellaneous), 1934-1935 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Distribution of Bequests, 1934-1936 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1934-1936 (Box 28, Folder 5)
- Series XI: Printed and Published Materials, 1931-1935
  This series is comprised of printed and published materials related to Elmer Ellsworth Brown and his role as Chancellor at New York Univeristy. Materials in this series consist of pamphlets, excerpts from academic journals, newspaper clippings, event programs, and a photograph of Brown's wife, Fanny.
  Arrangement
  Materials in this series were not arranged by an archivist. They were kept in the order in which they were found.
  - New York University Daily News, November 9, 1931 (Box Shared University Archives 150, Folder 1)
    This special edition of the newspaper was produced to commemorate the twentieth anniversary of Brown's chancellorship.
  - The Only Tragedy (pamphlet), 1931 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    This pamphlet documents an exchange of letters between Sir Michael E. Sadler and Elmer Ellsworth Brown.
  - "On the Heights" (promotional pamphlet by Harold DeWolf Fuller), undated (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - "Practical but not too practical" (promotional pamphlet by Harold DeWolf Fuller), undated (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - "Fathers of the Free" (poem by Elmer Ellsworth Brown), undated (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - New York University Promotional Fact Sheet (Centennial Celebration), 1931 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - New York University Ninety-Ninth Commencement Program, 1931 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - New York University 100th Anniversary Dinner Program, 1931 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - "A Conference of Universities" by Elmer Ellsworth Brown, 1933 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    Offprint of article in the Journal of Higher Education, Vol IV
  - Journal of Higher Education, 1933 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    This journal contains reviews of centennial publications: The Obligation of Universities to the Social Order and Journal of the Proceedings of a Convention of Literary and Scientigic Gentlemen.
  - Photostat of Clipping relating to Chancellor Brown's Resignation, 1932 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - "A Tribute to Elmer Ellsworth Brown" (Testimonial Dinner Program), May 3, 1933 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    This testimonial dinner took place on May 3, 1933 at the Waldorf-Astoria. It was presumably sponsored by the Alumni Federation.
  - Clipping from New York Herald-Tribune reporting on Chancellor Brown's Testimonial Dinner, May 4, 1933 (Box Shared University Archives 150, Folder 2)
  - Program of Memorial Service for Elmer Ellsworth Brown, 1935 (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - Legion d'Honneur, April 1935 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    This volume of Legion d'Honneur contains remarks made by John H. Finley about Elmer Ellsworth Brown.
  - Portrait of Fanny Eddy Brown, undated (Box 29, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings Announcing Death of Fanny Eddy Brown, 1932 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    Clippings taken from the New York Herald-Tribune, New York Times, Chicago Tribune, and The Wellesley Magazine